let's look at an example to understand
what the composition of relations is in
this diagram we have two relations the
relation R from a set a to a set b and a
relation s from the set B to the set C
here are those two relations written out
precisely as sets for example we can see
under the relation r one is related to T
given this arrow that shouldn't be
surprising in the relation s for example
we see that s relates to Beta which is
indicated by this Arrow here s is also
related to Alpha and in the relation R
we can see that one is also related to
lowercase R so hopefully the diagram and
the set notation are both clear what
would happen if we compose these
relations what would it mean to compose
the relation r with the relation s it
works out probably just how you expect
under the composite relation for example
three relates to gamma because the
relation R relates 3 to q and then s
relates Q to gamma so in total under the
composition 3 is related to gamma in
plain language the elements relate from
a to c if there's a connection between
them given these two relations here is
the entire composite relation written
out you can see how I've notated the
composition we'll talk about notation in
a second but just for another example
you can see that 4 is related to Alpha
and 4 is related to Beta because 4 is
related to S but then s is related to
both Alpha and to beta one is related to
R but R isn't related to anything in C
so one only appears in the composition
once given that one relates to T and
then T relates to gamma so that's the
only time that 1 a p here is in the
composite relation now let's take a
quick look at the general definition of
a composition of relations you can see
how an ordered pair x z is in the
composition of relations if there's some
middle element connecting x and z you
probably notice the notation I'm using
here is the same as what's used for
function composition because of that
sometimes a different notation is used
since this is a composition of relations
not functions this semicolon notation is
one such option you may also recall that
with function composition the second
function is typically applied first the
order is from right to left there
doesn't seem to be an agreed-upon
standard for the composition of
relations in this case I'm going
opposite the way that it's done for
function composition I'm going left to
right the relation R relates X to y I
but then s relates y to Z and so in
total the composition relates X to Z
this is a left to right direction just
be wary you might also see a composition
of relations following the typical order
for function composition which is right
to left and that's a quick overview of
what a composition of relations Is let
me know in the comments if you have any
questions and thank you very much for
watching
[Music]
existence